A Guide to the Elisabeth-Charlotte Harling Papers, 1950-1998
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Elisabeth-Charlotte Harling Papers, 1950-1998
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms99-007
1 box, 1 oversize; 5.3 cu. ft.
The Elisabeth-Charlotte Harling Papers consist of architectural drawings, photographs, specifications, correspondence, newspaper clippings, publications, and other materials organized in two series, documents and drawings.
Elisabeth-Charlotte Harling
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Elisabeth-Charlotte Harling Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1998.
Biographical Information
Elisabeth-Charlotte Harling was born on February 2, 1922 in Osnabrueck, Germany. She earned a diploma in Interior Design from the State School of Crafts and Applied Arts in Weimar. Her course of study included three months practical experience in a cabinetmaker's shop (1941-1943). In 1944 she attended the College of Architecture and Applied Arts in Weimar for a semester of architectural studies.
In 1944-1945, she was a teaching assistant in the history of architecture for Professor Denis Boniver in Weimar, and in 1945-1946, she worked at the British Area Works Office in Osnabrueck, gaining experience in interior design, construction supervision, and maintenance staff supervision. During 1946-1947 she worked for the architectural firm of Theo Burlage and Niebuhr in Osnabrueck, focusing on design and construction of residential and commercial buildings.
Harling returned to college in the Department of Architecture at the Technical University of Stuttgart, where she received her diploma in architecture. She traveled extensively in Europe, visiting Italy, Switzerland, France, Greece, and, England.
Harling began her professional career as an independent architect in 1953 when she designed and constructed the residence of Dr. Pante in Neuenkirchen, Germany.
In addition to designing as an independent architect, Harling was employed as architect and interior designer for several architectural firms. She had completprojects in France, Switzerland and Germany.
List of Firms and Projects
Suter and Suter in Basel, Switzerland, 1955-1961
1. Tropical Institute, Basel, Switzerland
2. Reception Pavilion of Sulzer, Winterthur, Switzerland
3. Administrative building of Suiselectra, Basel, Switzerland
Harling also worked for Suter and Suter as interior designer on several projects:
1. Offices for upper management of Winterthur, Paris, France
2. Expansion of Westfalenbank, Bochum, Germany
3. Coop Haus, Basel, Switzerland
4. New building of Swiss Credit Institute, Basel, Switzerland
5. Offices for upper management of Lonza, Lonza Highrise, Basel, Switzerland.
Otto H. Senn in Basel, Switzerland, 1961-1968
1. 1961 Administrative building of "Allgemeine Treuhand," Basel, Switzerland
2. 1962-1968 Library of the University Basel, Switzerland
3. 1966-1967 Planning of a residential development of 1280 units in Oberes Murifeld-Wittingkofen near Bern, Switzerland
4. 1968 Reorganization/reconstruction of the university library in Freiburg, Switzerland.
Otto H. Senn - design competitions, 1961-1968
1. 1962 Church Complex, Copenhagen, Denmark
2. 1965 Stadttheater (theater) in Basel, Switzerland
3. 1967-1968 School Im Moos, in Riehen near Basel, Switzerland.
State University and Building Department in Konstanz, Germany, 1969-1984
1. 1969-1972 Planning and design of Central Functions for a new University Library of the Konstanz University
2. 1974-1982 Design and construction supervision of a Natural Sciences Library at the new University of Konstanz
3. 1983-1984 Renovation of a historic administrative building in Konstanz.
Independent architect
1. 1965 Abbey St. Marie de Boulaur, Boulaur, France: reconstruction of a guesthouse of a Cistercian cloister
2. Vianney Hospital, Ueberlingen am Bodensee, Germany: reconstruction and interior design of a chapel
3. 1989 Convent St. Marie de Rieunette, near Carcassonne, France: Reconstruction of a destroyed Cistercian convent.
Publications and Presentations
1. 1966 article "Notizen zum Heutigen Wohnungsbau" (remarks on contemporary housing) in the "Schweizer Rundschau"
2. 1988-1997 lectures at the Senior Center Konstanz on "New Housing Projects for Senior Citizens in Stuttgart and Freiburg;" "How to Adjust a Residence for Use by Handicapped Persons," and "Introduction to Auditing Courses at the University of Konstanz".
Scope and Content
The Elisabeth-Charlotte Harling Papers consist of architectural drawings, photographs, specifications, correspondence, newspaper clippings, publications, and other materials organized in two series, documents and drawings. Most of the text of the materials is in German or French. The collection contains 171 drawings covering 18 different projects in which Harling participated while working in cooperation with several architectural firms, the State University and Building Department in Konstanz, Germany, and as an independent architect in France.
The drawings reflect Harling's activities as an interior designer and as an architect. The first folder contains original drawings (ink and pencil) while folders 2,3 and 4 contain printed drawings. The drawings reflect diverse projects, and include comprehensive floor plans, prospects, perspectives and several construction drawings. Additionally, several drawings document her work as interior designer.
During her career Harling participated in the realization of several important design projects while cooperating with diverse architectural offices, universities and as an independent architect. Some of these design projects are represented in the collection by drawings, publications, miscellaneous newspaper clippings, and photographs. In particular the collection contains a significant number of drawings and various related materials regarding the design of the Universitatsbibliothek in Basel, Switzerland (1962-1968). Harling participated in this architectural project while working for the architectural firm of Otto H. Senn. This design is documented with a significant number of original drawings (45), related publications, photographs of drawings and models, and newspaper clippings. Also included are several remarkable original hand colored drawings of the prospects and plans of the building.
While working for Suter and Suter, Harling helped in the design of the Swiss Credit Institute (1960) in Basel, Switzerland and in the realization of an office building for the upper management of Lonza, Lonza Highrise (1960), also in Basel. The two projects are documented in the collection through several drawings, photographs, and other miscellaneous material.
Finally, it is important to mention the drawings and related material regarding two projects that Harling developed while working with the State University and Building Department in Konstanz (Germany). As Architect in charge, she participated in the planning and design of the Central Functions for the new University Library (1969-1972) and in the design and construction supervision of the Natural Sciences Library (1974-1982) at the new University of Konstanz. The Universitatsbibliothek in Basel is represented in 45 drawings, the design for the Central Functions for a New University Library (1969-1972) of the Konstanz University in Germany in 25 drawings, and the Natural Sciences Library, 31 drawings.
Note: Some of Elisabeth-Charlotte Harling's papers were given to the Technical University Stuttgart.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by subject.
Contents List
- Curriculum Vitae, 1998. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Correspondence with Inge Horton, 1998-1999. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Photographs of Harling; model for the Naturwissenschaftliche Bibliothek, Universitat Konstanz; photographs of a lamp, 1978-1999. (Box-folder 1:3)
- La bibliotheque cantonale del' Universitaire, Freibourg, 1976. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Chronologische Aufstellung Meiner Arbeiten, 1950-1995. (Box-folder 1:5)
- (2) Drawing and photograph of Kapellen Erweiterung, 1952-1969. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Photographs of Abbaye Sainte Marie de Rieunette, 1998. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Garten und Literatur, 1988. (Box-folder 1:8)
- 1951-1952, (2) Drawings of Saarbrucken;1989, (1) Drawing of the Albert Ludwig Universitat, Freiburg; 1988-1989, Seminar: Ansicht des Cortile del Belvedere in Rome von Vatican Palast aus gesehen; 1984, Photographs and drawings of a table; n.d., Modelphotos of Schweizerische Nationalversicherung Basel;1966, Modelphotos of Theaterraum mit Orchestergraben, Basel;1950-1995, Miscellaneous photographs of several design projects;1967, Notizen zum Wohnbau heute in Schweizer Rundschau, 1967. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Negatives of Universitats Bibliothek, Basel, 1964-1967. (Box-folder 1:10)
- Schweizerische Bauzeitung, Der Bibliothek der Universitat, Basel, by G. Risch and A. Ostertag, 1969. (Box-folder 1:11)
- Newspapers clippings about the Univeristatsbibliothek in Basel, 1964-1992. (Box-folder 1:12)
- Photographs of the Universitats Bibliothek, Basel, 1996. (Box-folder 1:13)
- Basel Universitatsbibliothek, 1968. (Box-folder 1:14)
- (15) Drawings of the Neubau Universitatsbibliothek, Basel, 1963-1967. (Box-folder 1:15)
- Photographs of Universitats Bibliotek, Basel, 1965-1968. (Box-folder 1:16)
- Photographs of Universitatsbibliothek, Basel, n.d. (Box-folder 1:17)
- Miscellaneous newspapers clippings and publications about the Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1967-1983. (Box-folder 1:18)
- (1) Drawing of the Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1969. (Box-folder 1:19)
- (14) Drawings of the Universitat Konstanz Endstufe Giessberg and miscellaneous images and notes regarding the Universitat, Konstanz, 1969-1976. (Box-folder 1:20)
- (9) Drawings of the Neubau Universitatsbibliothek, Basel, 1958-1967. (Box-folder 1:21)
- (6) Drawings of the Neubau Universitatsbibliothek, Basel, 1958-1968. (Box-folder 1:22)
- Photographs of Naturwissenschaftliche Bibliothek, Universitat-Konstanz, n.d. (Box-folder 1:23)
- (6) Drawings of the Naturwissenschaftliche Bibliothek, Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1978-1981. (Box-folder 1:24)
- (8) Drawings of the Naturwissenschaftliche Bibliothek, Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1977-1979. (Box-folder 1:25)
- Miscellaneous photographs and (2) drawings of Naturwissenschaftliche Bibliothek, Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1974-1983. (Box-folder 1:26)
- (10) Drawings of Gepolsterter Stahlrohr-Stuhland Tische, Handschriften, Hofbau, 1964-1967. (Box-folder 1:27)
- (2) Drawings and photographs of Empfangspavillon, Basel, 1956. (Box-folder 1:28)
- (5) Drawings and photographs of Coop-Haus, Aeschenplatz, 1956-1958. (Box-folder 1:29)
- Winterthur, Paris, Societes Suisses D'Assurances, 1957-1959. (Box-folder 1:30)
- Images of the Basler Borse-Umbau, Basel, 1960-1961. (Box-folder 1:31)
- Images of Westfalenbank Bochum, Basel, 1958-1959. (Box-folder 1:32)
- (7) Drawings of the Schweizerische Kreditanstalt, Basel, 1960. (Box-folder 1:33)
- Photographs of a model for the Schweizerische Kreditanstalt, Basel; miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1958-1964. (Box-folder 1:34)
- (3) Drawings of the Cheminee Wohraum II, Basel, 1960. (Box-folder 1:35)
- Edificio Lonza, S.A., in Basilea, Switzerland; images and (2) drawings of the Lonza AG. Burogebaude, Basel, 1961-1962. (Box-folder 1:36)
- (1) Drawing of the Basler Kantonalbank, Basel, 1960. (Box-folder 1:37)
- Alfred-Escher-Haus-Personalrestaurant der Schweizerischen Kreditanstalt, Zurich; images of the Schweiz Kreditanstalt, Zurich, 1961-1962. (Box-folder 1:38)
- Clubhaus, Stuttgart, 1950 (Oversize 1)
  - Comprehensive plan and perspective.
  - Construction details.
  - Perspective of the interiors.
  - Front facade and perspective.
  - Front facades.
  - Floor plan.
  - Floor plan and perspective of interiors.
  - Floor plan and Section.
- Poster, UIFA, Berlin, 1984. (Oversize 1)
- Couvent de Rieunette, 1992-1994. (Oversize 1)
  - Isometric Perspective.
  - Isometric Perspective.
  - Design of the cells of the first floor.
  - Facade N-E.
  - Facade N-W.
  - Sketches of the front facade.
  - Facade S-W.
  - Facade S-W.
  - Facade of the aisle N-E.
  - Elevation of the facade.
  - Longitudinal section.
  - Longitudinal section.
  - Ground floor plan.
  - First floor plan.
  - Ground Floor.
  - Facade S-E.
  - Comprehensive plan.
- Erweiterung der Kapelle des Vianney-Hospital, Uberlingen, 1969-1970. (Oversize 1)
  - Plans, front facades, sections.
  - Plan and section of the Tabernackle.
  - Construction details of the Kirchenbaenke.
  - Plans, section, details of a chapel.
  - Design details of the altar.
  - Perspective of the interior of the chapel.
  - Perspective of the interior of the chapel.
- Cantine, Brussels, 1956.
  - Plan of the ground floor.
  - Elevations of the facades.
  - Perspective of the interiors.
- Universitatsbibliothek, Basel, 1961-1964.
  - Front facade - west side.
  - South facade.
  - Plan and fronts of a chair.
  - Perspective of the interiors.
  - Construction drawings for a perspective.
- Schulen "Im Moss," Basel, 1967. (Oversize 1)
  - Perspective.
  - Sections and front facades.
  - Sections and front facades.
  - General plans.
  - General plans.
  - General plans.
  - Perspective of the interiors.
  - Roof plan.
- Abbey St. Marie De Boulaur, 1965-1975. (Oversize 1)
  - Sketches of the interiors.
  - Design details of the bathroom.
  - Interior design of a single room.
  - Plans and section.
  - Plan.
  - Facades S-W, N-E.
  - Plan, facades and section.
  - Plans of the dormitories.
  - Front facades and Sections of the dormitories.
  - General plan.
- Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1973. (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous designs.
  - General plan.
- Dreigenerationenhaus, n.d. (Oversize 1)
  - Plans.
  - Plans.
- Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1972-1982. (Oversize 1)
  - Arbeitsplatzmobel.
  - Perspective of the interiors.
  - Perspective construction elements.
  - Perspective.
  - Sketches for assonometric drawings.
  - Sketches for assonometric drawings.
  - Sketches for assonometric drawings.
  - Sketches for assonometric drawings.
  - Construction drawings for the general plan.
  - General plan, section, sketches.
  - General plan, section, sketches.
  - General plan, section, sketches.
  - General plan, section, sketches.
  - Plan and section.
  - Plan level -1.33.
  - Plan level +2.67/+4.00.
  - Plan and facades.
  - Sketches for chairs, tables and benches.
  - Sketches for chairs, tables and benches.
  - Sketches for chairs, tables and benches.
  - Sketches for chairs, tables and benches.
  - Sketches for chairs, tables and benches.
  - Sketches for chairs, tables and benches.
- 2 Miscellaneous drawings, 1952. (Oversize 2)
- Planes and front facades of Saarbruecken, 1952. (Oversize 2)
- Construction details of Saarbruecken, 1951-1952. (Oversize 2)
- Plan for Platz der Weissen rose, Freiburg, 1989. (Oversize 2)
- Neubau Universitatsbibliothek, Basel, 1963-1967. (Oversize 2)
  - Perspective of the Treppenhalle.
  - Perspective of the Treppenhalle.
  - Perspective of the Katalog-Saal.
  - Perspective of the Zeitschriftenlesensaal.
  - Perspective of the Lesesaal.
  - Perspective of the Grosser Lesesaal.
  - Construction details.
  - Construction details of Abhorkabinen and Telefonkabinen.
  - Construction details of the Tur and Schrank.
  - Construction details of Zeitschriften table in Plexiglas.
  - Construction details of the Zeitschriftenlesesaal.
  - Planes and sections of the Musikzimmer.
  - Construction details.
  - Plans and sections prospects of Mappenschanke.
  - Construction details of Mappenschanke and Auskunftskorpus.
- Neubau Universitatsbibliothek, Basel, 1964-1967. (Oversize 2)
  - Construction details of Schreibmaschinenkorpus.
  - Construction details of Tisch Erfrischungs Raum.
  - Construction details of Tische Handschriften.
  - Details of Stahlrohrstuhl.
  - Sketches of Stahlrohrstuhl.
  - Sketches of Stahlrohrstuhl.
  - Plans and front and lateral facades of Stahlrohrstuhl.
  - Plan and front of Gepolsterter Stahlrohr.
  - Perspective of Stahlrohrstuhl.
  - Plan, front and lateral facades of Stahlrohrstuhl.
- Neubau Universitatsbibliothek, Basel, 1958-1964. (Oversize 2)
  - Construction details and general plan of Galerie Untersichten.
  - Front facade Hofbau Sud Botanischerkgarten.
  - Floor plan at level +3.05 m.
  - Prospect of a front facade Verwaltung West Schonbeinstrasse.
  - Prospect of the front facade Kopfbau Nord Bernoullistrasse.
  - Section of the building H-H.
  - Section of the building G-G.
  - Floor plan level +9.00 m Dachgeschoss.
  - Floor plan level +6.60 m Obergeschoss.
- Neubau Universitatsbibliothek, Basel, 1958-1961. (Oversize 2)
  - Floor plan level + 0.00m Hauptgeschoss.
  - Floor plan level - 2.97 m Erdgeschoss D.
  - Floor plan level - 6.27 m Untergeschoss.
  - Floor plan level - 7.70 Zwischenkeller.
  - Floor plan level - Klimazentrale.
  - Floor plan level - 10.45 m.
- Naturwissenschaftliche Bibliothek Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1978-1981. (Oversize 2)
  - Carrel aus mobilen elementen design and disposition into floor plan.
  - Design details: Ermittlung Negative and Positive Ecken.
  - Construction details: Montagewarne and Abgeh. Paneeldecken.
  - Construction details: Montagewarne and Abgeh. Paneeldecken.
  - Construction details: Metallfenster.
  - Construction details: Windfang-Terrassenanschluss.
- Naturwissenschaftliche Bibliothek Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1977-1979. (Oversize 2)
  - Miscellaneous construction details.
  - Miscellaneous construction details.
  - Construction details - Grundriss - Balkenlage.
  - Floor plan and details - Dachstuhl and Stutzendetails.
  - Floor plan Schalplan.
  - Floor plan Schalplan.
  - Floor plan Schalplan Fundamente.
  - Floor plan Betriebsstufe D Ebene Entwasserungs and Fundament plan.
- Naturwissenschaftliche Bibliothek Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1974-1977. (Oversize 3)
  - Prospect section - Betriebsstufe C2.
  - Detais of the facade.
- Naturwissenschaftliche Bibliothek Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1969. (Oversize 3)
  - Floor plan and details - Zentraler Bereich and Geisteswissenschaften.
- Naturwissenschaftliche Bibliothek Universitatsbauamt, Konstanz, 1969-1976. (Oversize 3)
  - Floor plan and details - Bankelemente Testeingebaut.
  - Design studies for a table.
  - Design details for Arbeitstisch.
  - Design details for Arbeitsplatzmobel.
  - Construction details for Stutzmauerisolierung am Forum.
  - Construction details for Treppe von Eingangshalle level +0,63 m.
  - Construction details for Oberlichter im Informationszentrum.
  - Construction detail for Aussentreppe.
  - Construction details and floor plan - Zentraler Bereich and Geisteswissensch.
  - Prospect section of Betriebsstufe B Zentraler Bereich Sud and Ostansich.
  - Floor plan Informationszentrum Grundriss.
  - Floor plan Betriebsstufe B - Zentraler Bereich.
  - Cross section Baustufe A/B Buro.
  - Comprehensive floor plan.
- Empfangspavillon, Basel, 1956. (Oversize 4)
  - Prospects.
  - Construction details.
- Coop Haus-Aeschenplatz, 1957-1958. (Oversize 4)
  - Design details.
  - Design details of a bench.
  - Interior design details for a restaurant.
  - Design details for the composition of an interior front.
  - Perspective of bank-kassenhalle.
- Schweizerische Kreditanstalt, Basel, 1960. (Oversize 4)
  - Perspective of exterior of the building.
  - Perspective of the exterior of the building.
  - Design details - Schreibtische.
  - Design details - Schreibtische and Hocker.
  - Design details for an interior front.
  - Design details for a chair.
  - Design details for a chair.
- Cheminee Wohnraum II, Basel, 1960. (Oversize 4)
  - Perspective of the interiors.
  - Perspective of the interiors.
  - Perspective of the interiors.
  - Edifice Lonza S.A., Basilea, Switzerland.
  - Perspective of the interiors.
  - Floor plan.
- Basel Kantonalbank, 1960. (Oversize 4)
  - Construction details for the design of the facade.